<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vertuous daughter A sermon preached at Saint Maries in Warwicke, at the funerall of the most vertuous and truely religious young gentlewoman, Mistresse Cicely Puckering, daughter and co-heire to the right worshipfull, Sir Thomas Puckering, knight and baronet, the fourteenth day of Aprill, 1636. By Iohn Bryan, parson of Barford.</title>
            <author>Bryan, John, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849484</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 704:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vertuous daughter A sermon preached at Saint Maries in Warwicke, at the funerall of the most vertuous and truely religious young gentlewoman, Mistresse Cicely Puckering, daughter and co-heire to the right worshipfull, Sir Thomas Puckering, knight and baronet, the fourteenth day of Aprill, 1636. By Iohn Bryan, parson of Barford.</title>
                  <author>Bryan, John, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 21, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Lawrence Chapman, and are to be sold at his shop in Holborne, at Chancery lane end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VERTVOVS DAVGHTER.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at Saint <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Warwicke</hi> at the Funerall of the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and truely religious young Gentlewoman, Miſtreſſe <hi>Cicely Puckering,</hi> Daughter and Co-heire to the right Worſhipfull, Sir <hi>Thomas Puckering,</hi> Knight and Baronet, the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1636.</p>
            <p>BY IOHN BRYAN, <hi>Parſon of Barford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 8.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Out of the mouthes of Babes and Sucklings haſt thou ordained ſtrength.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> for <hi>Lawrence Chapman,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Holborne, at Chancery lane end. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull, Sir THOMAS PVCKERING, Knight and Baronet, and to his vertuous and religious Lady, increaſe of all ſaving graces here, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting peace and reſt in heaven.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon preached at the funerall of your deareſt childe, (who was a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saint on earth, and is now a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one in heaven) I doe humbly dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to you both; it being yours by all manner of right, and the beſt Preſent J am able to preſent your Worſhips with. My poore paines taken herein, J heartily acknowledge to deſerve neither yours, nor the acceptation of any that are judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but the ſpeeches which proceeded from the heavenly mouth of your bleſſed Daughter, which are here related, deſerve in the judgement of wiſe and good men, to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in letters of Gold, and to be known and read of all men, being full of life and power to quicken the dulleſt ſoule to a love and liking of the wayes of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>The deſire to heare this Sermon preached, was great, and generall, as appeared by the great confluence of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of Towne and Country; neither is it doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but that ſome good was then wrought upon many ſouls</p>
            <p>And the deſire to have it publiſhed, is greater and more generall, there being hope conceived that much glory may be brought to God, and much edification to men, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the worke of God upon ſo tender yeares.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:3"/>
            <p>Your Worſhips have much honoured God and your ſelves, by bearing ſo great a triall with ſuch admirable patience and comfort. What remaineth, but that you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſet before your eyes this matchleſſe patterne which proceeded from your owne bowels, for your imitation; that as you were inſtruments to give her a temporall life, ſo ſhe (though dead, yet ſpeaking) may be an happy inſtrument, though not to give, yet to increaſe and maintaine the life of grace and conſolation in your ſoules.</p>
            <p>You have begunne to cleave to Chriſt with firme de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull purpoſe of heart; and the world obſerveth, that you are already rich gainers by this great loſſe. Goe on I beſeech you, and grow daily in the exemplary practiſe of a really religious life, being fully aſſured, that he whoſe glory you ſeeke, and whoſe yoke you beare, will in due time make up this breach, and recompence this loſſe, if not in the ſame kinde, (which I pray and hope) yet in ſome other, which ſhall be moſt for his glory, and your comfort in the end.</p>
            <p>Neither is there cauſe that you ſhould overmuch lament the loſſe of this one childe, ſeeing God hath bleſſed you with many children, though but one living, (upon whom, God Almighty double his bleſſings) For (to omit many, whoſe parents in effect you are) may I not call thoſe ſixe poore children in <hi>Warwicke</hi> for whom you have provided honeſt and profitable trades and callings, every ſeven yeares ſucceſſively to the worlds end. (of whoſe death there is no feare while the common wealth and lawes continue in life) your children?</p>
            <p>But fearing, leſt J ſhould exceed the bounds of an Epiſtle deſiring your favourable acceptance of this poore expreſſion of my thankefull minde for your many favours, J humbly take my leave, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s much obliged, and in the Lord ever to be commanded,</hi> Iohn Bryan.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14634:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Vertuous <hi>DAVGHTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PRO. 31.29.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Many Daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter ſpends it ſelfe for the moſt part in the deſcription &amp; commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a vertuous woman. The exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium or beginning of the encomium, is in the tenth verſe; <hi>Who can finde a vertuous woman? for her price is farre above rubies.</hi> The concluſion of it is in the four laſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whereof my Text is one.</p>
            <p>Wherein the holy Ghoſt giveth her (as we ſee) a moſt ample teſtimony and commendation by way of compariſon, for hee compareth her not with a vitious one (whom it is no great grace to ſurpaſſe) but with the vertuous, nor with one onely, but with many: all which (he witneſſeth) ſhe doth not onely equallize, but farre excell. <hi>Many daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maine leſſon which the Spirit of God intendeth to teach us in this context, and eſpecially in theſe words, is this, <hi>That ſuch as doe vertuouſly, may and ſhould bee praiſed:</hi> yea, the more vertuouſly any doe, the more praiſe and commendation is due to them. This good woman deſcribed in this chapter, is (as you ſee) not onely poſitively, but ſuperl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tively praiſed.</p>
            <p>For the explication of this point,<note place="margin">Explication.</note> nothing needs ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſave what is meant by doing vertuouſly.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14634:4"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What it is to doe vertuouſly.</note>Morall Philoſophers define vertue thus. It is (ſay they) an habit of the minde, acquired and confirmed by cuſtome, uſe and practiſe, enabling a man to rule his appetite, and to diſcharge the duties of his calling in a laudable manner.</p>
            <p>In fewer words thus; It is an elective habit, inclining the will to well-doing.</p>
            <p>Now to wel-doing, they teach<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſtot. eth. lib. 2. cap. 4.</note> foure things to be requiſite.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thing or ſubject matter of the action, be in it ſelfe lawfull and good; even ſuch as is approved and warranted by the judgement of wiſe men: for this they make the rule of vertue.<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 2. cap. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 That the agent both know and purpoſe the doing of it: for he that doth a good action ignorantly or raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cannot be ſaid to doe well, ſeeing ſcience and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell are the foundation of every good worke: for as to <hi>him that knoweth to doe good, and doth it not, to him it is ſinne:</hi> ſo to him that doth good, and knoweth it not, or purpoſeth it not, it is ſinne alſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That his end be right: for hee that doth a good worke for ſome by-reſpect, and not out of love to goodneſſe, and for it owne ſake, he may doe ſomething which may be materially good, but it is, at the beſt, far from being well done.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That he continue and hold out unto the end in his purpoſe and endeavour of doing well: for perſeverance is the complement and crowne of vertue.</p>
            <p>Divinity defines it thus. It is a gift of Gods Spirit, and a part of regeneration, whereby a man is made apt and able to <hi>deny all ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world.</hi> And to doe thus, is to doe vertuouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Confirmation </seg>1</label> For confirmation of this truth, firſt I will give you ſome examples of vertuous women, both out of the old and new Teſtament, who are commended by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14634:4"/> holy Ghoſt for doing vertuouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jael</hi> the wife of <hi>Heber</hi> the Ken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.24.25.26. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.</note> is much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Propheteſſe for her courage in killing Siſera.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abigal,</hi> the wife of <hi>Nabal</hi> the Carmelite, is praiſed for her diſcretion, and is ſaid to be a woman of <hi>good underſtanding:</hi> and <hi>David</hi> bleſſeth her and her adviſe, whereby ſhe preſerved her whole family from ruine.</p>
            <p>The vertues of <hi>Ruth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth</hi> 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Naomies</hi> daughter in law, were generally taken notice of, and ſhe therefore ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of all the people.</p>
            <p>The holy women in old time are commended for <hi>truſting in God, adorning themſelves modeſtly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>and for ſubjection to their husbands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour doth largely commend the ſinfull peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent woman in the ſeventh of Saint <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 7.44.45 46.47. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.3.</note> and in the next chapter, <hi>Mary Magdalen, Ioanna</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna,</hi> are noted and commended for their liberality to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Chriſt: <hi>They miniſtred to him of their owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what ſhall I ſay more? for the time would faile me to tell of <hi>Rebekah, Deborah, Hannah, Lydia, Priſcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, Doreas, Tryphena,</hi> and <hi>Tryphoſa;</hi> and above all, the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> our Lords Mother.</p>
            <p>The like inſtances may be given of men alſo:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as of <hi>Hananiah,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>That he feared God above many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of <hi>Joſiah</hi> it is recorded, <hi>That like unto him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.25</note> 
               <hi>there was no King before him, neither aroſe there after him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny like unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or <hi>Iob,</hi> God himſelfe ſpeakes thus to Satan.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Haſt thou conſidered my ſervant</hi> Iob, <hi>how there is none like him in all the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond proofe of the point is from Gods Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Confirmation </seg>2</label> he hath engaged himſelfe that ſuch as live vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, ſhall bee praiſed; ſee the verſe before my Text. <hi>Her children riſe up, and call her bleſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 31.22.</note> 
               <hi>her husband alſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14634:5"/> and he ſhall praiſe her:</hi>
               <note place="margin">30.</note> and the verſe after my text, <hi>A woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.16.10 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6.</note>So alſo he ſaith elſewhere, <hi>A gratious woman retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth honour:</hi> and againe, <hi>The memory of the juſt is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> and the Prophet <hi>David</hi> likewiſe ſaith, <hi>The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>firm.</hi>
               </note>Thirdly, God hath given commandement to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and praiſe thoſe that live vertuouſly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.31.</note> 
               <hi>Give her of the fruit of her hands, and let her works praiſe her in the gates,</hi> (ſaith the holy Ghoſt in the laſt verſe of this Chapter) that is, praiſe her for her workes publikely.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13 7.</note>See a generall command given by <hi>Paul, Render to all their dues, tribute to whom tribute, honour to whom ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that honour is the due reward of vertue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>&amp; lib. 4. cap. 3.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus Deis, laus verò bonis v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ris tributuda eſt. Recte facta l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uda e hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum eſt. Phil. <hi>4.8.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>Firſt, heathen men ſaw and taught. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the ſecond booke of his Ethickes, teacheth, that praiſe is due to vertue. Hee ſaith alſo elſe where, that though a wiſe man ſhould not deſire praiſe, yet praiſe ought to be given to them that live according to the rules of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Againe, another ſaith, Incenſe is due to the gods, and ſo is praiſe to good men: yea, they eſteemed this a point of honeſty. It is an honeſt thing (ſaith one of them) to commend wel-doing: now honeſty ſtandeth (you know) in giving every man his owne. But to let heathens paſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the holy Ghoſt hath tyed praiſe to vertue. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>If there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe:</hi> implying, that where there is vertue, there muſt be alſo praiſe. I will conclude this proofe with that notable place in the 26. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> where Chriſt gives command,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.13.</note> that <hi>whereſoever the Goſpell ſhould be preached, there ſhould alſo that, that the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had done to him, be told for a memoriall of her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Confirmation </seg>4</label> Fourthly and laſtly, there is good uſe of praiſing thoſe that do vertuouſly, much profit may redound hereby.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14634:5"/>
            <p>Firſt, to the praiſers themſelves. One ſaith,<note place="margin">Bonum laudare non laudato ſed laudantibus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt. Aug.</note> To praiſe the good, profiteth not the praiſed, but the praiſers: for who will not be moved to labour for that good in themſelves, which they commend in others?</p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſuch as heare them praiſed: for they by this meanes will be ſtirred up.</p>
            <p n="1">1 To Thankſgiving to God, for giving ſuch grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men. <hi>We give thankes</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>and the Father of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, ſince we heard of your faith in Chriſt Ieſus, and of the love which ye have to all the Saints.</hi> And this effect we finde alſo of the liberality of the Corinthians;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>For the adminiſtration of the ſervice of theirs not onely ſupplyed the want of the Saints, but was abundant alſo by many thankeſgivings to God: while by the experiment of that miniſtration, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glorified God for their profeſſed ſubjection to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad ipſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dabilium un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verſorum ung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem.</note> Thus praiſe comes to be referred to the Author of all things praiſe-worthy.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To imitate what they heare praiſed: <hi>your zeale,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the Corinthians) <hi>hath provoked ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> for as fire when it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raked into, ſends forth greater heate, and light to them that ſit about it: and as pretious oyntment, if it be ſtirred or poured fourth, doth caſt a ſweeter ſmell to all thoſe that are neere it: even ſo the praiſes of vertuous and godly perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mentioned, will yeeld no ſmall edification to thoſe that heare them.</p>
            <p>Before I come to application, I will briefly anſwer this queſtion: namely,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> Whether ought we rather to praiſe the living, or the dead for wel-doing?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We have Chriſts example for both, and therefore both are undoubtedly lawfull, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.10. we finde him praiſing the living.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>I have not found</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of the Cenmrion) <hi>ſo great faith, no not in Jſrael, Joh.</hi> 5.35. he giveth an illuſtrious <hi>encomium</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14634:6"/> of the dead:<note place="margin">Iob. 5.35.</note> for ſpeaking there of <hi>John,</hi> whom <hi>Herod</hi> had beheaded, he ſaith, <hi>Hee was a burning and a ſhining light</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of the two it is ſafer, and leſſe ſubject to excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and danger, to praiſe the dead, and more profitable for two reaſons,<note place="margin">Nec laudantem adulatio movet, nec audatum elatio tentat, in nat. S. Euſeb. Lauda navigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis felicitatem, ſed eum perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerit ad po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum, lauda du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem, ſed cum perductus eſt ad triumphum. id. ibid.</note> (<hi>Ambroſe</hi> gives them) becauſe then (ſaith he) fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tery will not move the praiſer, nor vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory tempt the praiſed. Therefore <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us to <hi>judge none bleſſed before their death.</hi> Wee may beſt commend the Saylers happineſſe, when hee is arrived at the haven: and the Souldiers valour when he hath wonne the field.</p>
            <p>This doctrine is pregnant, of profitable uſes. It may ſerve by way of inference to informe our judgements.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inference. </seg>1</label> 1 That it is not ſufficient to have the theory or knowledge of vertue onely, but practice muſt be added to ſpeculation. It is not vertue to know good and evill, but to doe good, and eſchew evill. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Jf ye know theſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.17 <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>happy are ye if ye doe them.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are they that heare the word of God and keepe it:</hi> implying, that the knowledge of Gods word, and bare underſtanding of the myſteries of ſalvation, maketh no man happy: but <hi>who ſo looketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perfect law of liberty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>and continueth therein, hee being not a forgetfull hearer, but a doer of the worke, this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſhall be bleſſed in his deed.</hi> Reade <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.24. to the end.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inference. </seg>2</label> 2 That it is not enough to ſpeake well, but wee muſt alſo doe well. The Scribes and Phariſes have this brand of hypocriſie ſet upon them by our Saviour Chriſt.<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus.</note> 
               <hi>They ſay and doe not, Matth.</hi> 23.3.<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Arl. Eth. lib. 2. cap. 4.</note> Too many in our dayes are like thoſe Scribes and Phariſes; for though their tongues be ſteept in religion, yet their lives are ſtained with foule abhominations, to the great ſcandall of their glorious profeſſion. Let not theſe men thinke that God is any whit at all pleaſed to heare
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14634:6"/> them ſpeake piouſly of him, and his kingdome, and the righteouſneſſe thereof, while they refuſe to admit his kingdome into their hearts, and to expreſſe the power of it in their lives. Nay, he is greatly herewith offended.<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Agell. lib. 17. cap. 19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.28 29. <hi>Tit</hi> 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>What haſt thou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to doe, to take my covenant in thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteth my words behinde thee,</hi> and liveſt unjuſtly and unchaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? The Iſraelites ſpake well to <hi>Moſes</hi> by Gods owne teſtimony. <hi>They have well ſaid in all that they have ſpoken; but he wiſheth, Oh that there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would feare me and keepe my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</hi> They proved afterward ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of, who <hi>profeſſed they knew God, but in their workes they denyed h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, being abhominable, diſobedient, and to every good worke reprobate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inference: </seg>3</label> 3 That we muſt not content our ſelves to doe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and religious workes, but wee muſt have a care that we doe them in a vertuous and religious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore they muſt proceed from a good root and fountaine, even a principle of regeneration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. <hi>A corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit. And to them that are defiled and unbeleeving, is nothing pure,</hi> but their beſt workes are defiled in Gods eyes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they muſt be done in obedience to Gods command. Reſpect to his will muſt be the ground and motive of our working.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Gods glory muſt be our utmoſt end:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we doe, we muſt doe all to his glory. Jf any man ſpeake, let him ſpeake as the Oracles of God; if any man miniſter, let him doe it as of the ability which God hath given him, that God in all things may be glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, wee muſt be abundant alwayes in good workes, unwearied in wel-doing. And finally, when we have done all that we can, we muſt ſay we are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants,</hi> wee have done but that which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14634:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14634:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14634:8"/> was our duty to doe.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inference. </seg>4</label> 4 That we ought not to content our ſelves with an ordinary meaſure of grace and vertue, but we muſt ſeeke to excell others, like this woman in my Text, who excelled all other daughters that did vertuouſly. It is the Apoſtles injunction.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Eph</hi> 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 5.47.</note> 
               <hi>Seeke that ye may excell.</hi> And againe, <hi>See that ye walke exactly or preciſely,</hi> not as the ordinary ſort of Profeſſors walke. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>That if ye ſalute your brethren onely, what doe you more than others?</hi> implying, that wee muſt exceed others in weldoing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math</hi> 5.48.</note> ſetting God himſelfe before us as our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne: <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inference. </seg>5</label> 5 That we ought not to praiſe, but rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and condemne vitious perſons. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of ſome diſorders among the Corinthians, ſaith thus,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I praiſe you in this? I praiſe you not.</hi> As who ſhould ſay, I have no warrant to commend ſuch as walke diſorderly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That they that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the law, praiſe the wicked;</hi> branding them with a marke of Apoſtaſie from Gods law, that ſpeake well of evill men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.20.</note>Againſt theſe the Prophet pronounceth a woe. <hi>Woe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to them that call good evill, and evill good.</hi> Theſe doe what in them lyeth, to make Gods commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of none effect.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 10 7.</note> For he hath threatned, that <hi>the name of the wicked ſhall rot and ſtinke.</hi> Let not therefore ungodly ones, who have neither the habit nor the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of any grace or vertue in them, whoſe ſoules ſerve for no other uſe, then the ſoules of ſwine; to keepe their bodies from putrifying (as if they were borne for no other end than to conſume Gods good creatures) expect any praiſe either in life or death,<note place="margin">Fruges conſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> except it bee from flatterers: for as to them who continue patiently in weldoing, ſhall be glory and honour: ſo to them who obey not the truth, but obey unrighteouſneſſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14634:8"/> ſhall be ſhame and confuſion of face, both here and hereafter. Reade <hi>Ierem.</hi> 22.17.18.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> expoſtulates thus with his friends,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Will you ſpeake wickedly for God, and talke deceitfully for him?</hi> If wee may not ſpeake falſly to glorifie God, much leſſe may we to glorifie men. Thus ſhould we juſtifie the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſo make our ſelves abhomination unto God. Nay, 'tis dangerous for men to affect and receive praiſe and glory, when they deſerve it not. Reade <hi>Acts</hi> 12.22.23.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inference. </seg>6</label> 6 That ſuch as unfainedly deſire and endeavour to doe vertuouſly, ſhall not faile to have praiſe both of God and men.</p>
            <p>Firſt of God, who hath promiſed, that although the credit of his ſervants may for a ſeaſon be covered with a cloud of reproach (as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> was) <hi>yet hee will bring forth their righteouſneſſe as the light, and their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the noone day.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.29.</note> hee that is <hi>a Iew inwardly,</hi> (that is really religious, who hath the inward power of godlineſſe, as well as the outward forme) <hi>ſhall have praiſe of God.</hi> And this indeed is the true praiſe.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18.</note> 
               <hi>For not he that commendeth himſelfe</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) is approved, but whom the Lord commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, of men. <hi>Men will praiſe thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.18.</note> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt <hi>when thou doſt well to thy ſelfe.</hi> Now a man then doth good to himſelfe when he doth vertuouſly.</p>
            <p>And not onely the common ſort of men, but alſo Magiſtrates and men in high place will commend and encourage us. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that <hi>Rulers are not a terrour to good workes, but to evill:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>will thou then not be afraid of the power? doe that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14634:9"/>
            <p>To come to the occaſion in hand, for I muſt wave all other generall uſes for want of time) by this that hath been ſaid, it may appeare, that I have warrant ſufficient, ſigned with Gods owne hand, to ſpeake in the praiſe and commendation of this young Gentlewoman, whoſe funerall rites wee now celebrate; foraſmuch as ſhe hath deſerved praiſe, having not onely done vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but excelled all others of her ſexe and age (take them both together) that I ever heard or knew of: for when ſhee dyed, ſhee was little more then <hi>twelve yeares of age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides, all that hath beene ſpoken for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and conveniencie of this practiſe of praiſing the dead, I have for my patterne and precedents here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, not onely many late divines, who have in thoſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Sermons which they preached at the burials of godly perſons, beene exceeding large in their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and were never yet excepted againſt for flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. But alſo many antient Fathers, who not onely in their conſolatory Letters written to them which loſt their friends, have inſerted large praiſes of them: but alſo in their Sermons at their funerals have done the like. Among others, <hi>Ierome</hi> is moſt noted, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he call flatterers <hi>ſparkles of the divell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diaboli.</note> yet none ever more exceeded in the commendation of any, then he of that vertuous and godly Matron <hi>Paula,</hi> both in his Sermon which he preached at her buriall in <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem,</hi> in a very great aſſembly of ſundry nations, and alſo in his Epiſtle written <hi>ad Euſtochium,</hi> which hee entituleth, <hi>the Epitaph of Paula.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>qu.</hi> 132.</note>True it is (as they teach in Schooles) that to praiſe a man for that which is not praiſe worthy, or more then is meet, or not for a right end, is ſinfull and cannot be juſtified: but with due cautions to commend, cannot be juſtly cenſured.</p>
            <p>I will not therefore put on that reſolution which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14634:9"/> 
               <hi>Cicero</hi> once did; I will not, ſaid he, be a praiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r,<note place="margin">Nol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ne videar adulator.</note> leſt I ſhould ſeeme a flatterer; for ſo I ſhould not onely wrong the dead, (in robbing her of her due honour, although ſhe being received into the ſociety of Saints in heaven, needeth not our praiſes, more than our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,) but I ſhould alſo deale perfidiouſly both with God and you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, with God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.15.</note> in hiding <hi>a glorious candle under a buſhell</hi> which he lighted for others to ſee and worke by; and whoſe command to his Apoſtles I have juſt cauſe in this caſe to apply to my ſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> 
               <hi>What I tell you in darkeneſſe, that ſpeake ye in light, and what ye heare in the eare, that preach upon the houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, with you, in keeping from you that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious treaſure which may haply enrich you for ever. One compares the words of Saints to <hi>pure ſilver;</hi> the more you have of them, the wealthier you are.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.11.</note> Our Saviour cals them <hi>pearles:</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayes they <hi>are like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure I am, all that heard this childe ſpeake oft in her health, but eſpecially the day before, and that they ſhod died, (as the ſun ſhines moſt gloriouſly at his ſorting) did wonder at her gratious words, and might well ſay, never childe ſpake like this childe: ſo that we who heard her utter ſuch divine ſaying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſo roundly, and in ſuch an emphaticall manner, were forced to cry c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Doubtleſſe wee have heard ſtrange things to day.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e doubted, but that the promiſe which Chriſt made to his Apoſtles, was in a degree made good unto her, <hi>It ſhall be given you what ye ſhall ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>for it is not you that ſpeake, but the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You know our Saviours ſaying to the Phariſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: teaching us thereby to judge of the heart by the mouth, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he life give not the tongue the lye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.34.35.</note> 
               <hi>Out of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the heart the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeaketh. A good man out of the good treaſure of his heart, bringeth forth good
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14634:10"/> things.</hi> The good things which this deare Hand-maid of the Lord brought out of the treaſure of her heart, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued it to be truely good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5 6.7.</note>The chaine of Chriſtian graces ſpoken of by <hi>Peter,</hi> did adorne and beautifie her ſweet ſpirit: neither was any one linke of that golden chaine wanting in her, as might eaſily be evinced by demonſtrative evidences. But my purpoſe is onely to inſtance in three of thoſe graces: whereof when ye have heard undoubted proof, ye may then doe like him, who by the length and big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Hercules</hi> his foot,<note place="margin">Agellius. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> gathered the proportion of his whole body.</p>
            <p>The graces or vertues I ſhall inſtance in, are <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, piety,</hi> and <hi>patience:</hi> they are the Cardinall graces on which all others hang and turne, and theſe were very evidently diſcernable in her, even to ſuch as had but halfe an eye.</p>
            <p>And firſt to give ſome evidences of her <hi>knowledge,</hi> the Apoſtle taxeth certaine women in his time, who <hi>were alwayes learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> whom he therefore calleth <hi>ſilly women.</hi> She was none of thoſe women, but might true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay with <hi>David; J have more underſtanding than all my teachers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.99 100.</note> 
               <hi>J underſtand more then the Ancients.</hi> And the truth of this appeareth by the confeſſion of her beſt teachers, that they never received ſo much edification by any of her yeares, as by her words: as alſo of the Doctour that was with her, who profeſſed that hee never heard any childe ſpeake with more judgement in all his life.</p>
            <p>She did indeed deſire to be inſtructed by mee, her words were theſe. <hi>J pray you tell mee what courſe I ſhall take to live this ſhort time that I have to live, as I ought?</hi> Deare ſoule, I needed to receive inſtruction of thee. God ſaw my need, and therefore ſent me ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably unto thee: and I have learned of thee, better
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14634:10"/> then ever I did before, both how to live, and dye hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle exhorts us to <hi>be children in malice;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>not ſo in underſtanding.</hi> But oh that we were all like this childe in underſtanding! For ſuch was her knowledge, farre beyond her yeares, not confuſed, but diſtinct; not ſwelling, but humbling; not like the light of the Moon, but of the Sunne: a favorie affecting and hearing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: it warmed her owne heart, and ours alſo.</p>
            <p>Take one proofe of her knowledge in religion, long before her ſickneſſe. When the Nurſes childe in the houſe was drowned, and the Mother mourned ſore for it, ſhe gave her this grave counſell: <hi>Seeing Gods will is done in taking away your childe, take heed of offending God by murmuring: doe we not daily pray that Gods will may be done? and therefore wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it is done, we ſhould bee content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare alſo ſome paſſages in her ſickneſſe, which prove that ſhe was indeed indued with ſound knowledge and judgement.</p>
            <p>Being asked occaſionally whether Chriſt would heale her of her ſickneſſe, ſeeing he never refuſed to heale any; She anſwered, <hi>J beleeve that hee can doe it, but J cannot beleeve that he will heale the ſickneſſe of my body, but by death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, being asked whether ſhe thought God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted her in anger, or in love; She anſwered, <hi>Truely J cannot tell, but J know he hath cauſe to doe it in anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, telling us how Satan had long tempted her to doubt of her ſalvation, <hi>She ſaid, her hope was that ſhe did belong to God, becauſe Satan was ſo buſie with her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond grace or vertue that evidenced it ſelfe in her, and wherein we ſhould all labour to imitate her, was <hi>piety</hi> or <hi>godlineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come. And it conſiſts of three
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14634:11"/> parts, or there are three graces required to make one truely pious: viz. 1 Selfe-denyall. 2 Sanctification. 3 Devotion.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Selfe-deniall, the neceſſity whereof appeares by theſe ſpeeches of our Saviour:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26.</note> 
               <hi>If any man will come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, let him deny himſelfe;</hi> and againe, <hi>if any man come to me, and hate not his Father and Mother, and Wife and Children, and Brethren and Siſters; yea, and his owne life alſo, he cannot be my diſciple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this grace was not onely in truth, but in a great meaſure in her, will appeare if we conſider five ſorts of things wherein ſhe had denyed her ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 All earthly profits and contentments. It was my firſt queſtion to her; are you willing to leave the world? her anſwer was, <hi>yea truely, for I ſee nothing in this world that ſhould move me to deſire to live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Bodily eaſe and freedome from paine: for being almoſt tyred with a lingring ſickneſſe, and this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on put to her; Whether had you rather continue in this miſery ſtill, or commit a ſinne to be releaſed of it? Shee anſwered cheerefully, <hi>J had rather continue thou ſicke as J am, then commit any ſinne to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Her Parents: for being asked whether ſhee were willing to leave her Parents, and goe to Chriſt, She an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>I love my Father and my Mother dearely, but J love them lower then Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Her owne merits and righteouſneſſe: for when I demanded of her what ground of hope ſhe had to goe to heaven, her anſwer was, <hi>My hope is in the death and reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> But have you nothing on your ſelfe, ſaid I, to take comfort in? <hi>No truely,</hi> ſaid ſhee, <hi>I finde no good at all in my ſelfe, but a great deale of evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 Her life. She never ſmiled but twiſe in her ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, (that I took notice of) and both thoſe ſmiles were at the mention of her death. Once when I told her,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14634:11"/> that death would cure her of al her infirmities: <hi>oh I,</hi> ſaid ſhe, and ſmiled, <hi>and my deſire is to dye, which is farre better than to live.</hi> Againe, I asked her, whether had you rather (if you might have your choiſe) recover, and be matched to the greateſt Noble man in the world, or dye and be matched with Chriſt? <hi>She ſmiled againe, and ſaid, I had rather dye, for there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them;</hi> you meane, no compariſon, ſaid I: <hi>yea,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>There is no compariſon betweene the greateſt Lord, and Ieſus Chriſt; I meaned there is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond part or branch of piety, is Sanctification or regeneration, which is nothing elſe, but a ſtamping of the Image of God upon the ſoule,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> and the writing of his law in the heart; a partaking of the divine nature: a ſpirituall principle or divine inſtinct, inclining the ſoule upward unto God.</p>
            <p>That ſhe was partaker of this new birth, and had an heart throughly ſanctified, will appeare by two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 She was throughly humbled for her ſinnes: for <hi>She complained that ſhe had forſaken God, and broken that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which ſhe made with him in Baptiſme, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſerved no comfort thence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She feared that though ſhe mourned for ſinne, yet God would not accept it, becauſe ſhe was not grieved enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She ſaid,</hi> moreover, <hi>that ſhe was weary and laden with ſinne, more than with ſickneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, being exhorted to call to minde for her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the promiſes of the Goſpell, ſhe anſwered with griefe, and iterated it; <hi>Truely I have beene much too blame in neglecting to reade the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe and many more ſignes ſhe had of a ſoule ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly humbled for her ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There appeared divers expreſſions of divine and gratious impreſſions in her, which were infallible cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of ſanctification: as namely,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14634:12"/>1 Poverty of ſpirit: ſhe complained of her want of grace, ſaying; <hi>ſhe had very little grace, or rather none at all in her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Her hungring and thirſting after grace: <hi>Oh, I would give,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>any thing for grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Her hatred of ſinne, and love of Chriſt, eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in ſome former anſwers.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Her humility mixt with faith; for hearing me ſay, that her heavenly husband had prepared a place in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84 10.</note> whither ſhe was haſting; <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>Let me have the loweſt place there, and I ſhall thinke my ſelfe happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10 2.</note>The third thing requiſite to make one godly, is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. It is ſaid of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> that he was a devout man, and ſo it may be ſaid truely of this childe, that ſhe was a devout childe: for ſhee held in her judgement, and profeſſed with her mouth, the true religion of God; which gives all to Gods free grace, and leaves man none occaſion of boaſting in himſelfe. You heard before how freely ſhe renounced all worth in herſelfe, and ſought for all her comfort out of her ſelfe, onely in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, ſhe made conſcience of the duties of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: was fearefull of an oath: <hi>ſtrict</hi> in ſanctifying the Lords day. She was frequent in reading the Scriptures, and deſirous to heare them read, when ſhe could not reade her ſelfe, (becauſe of the ſoreneſſe of her eyes) and yet ſhe thought her ſelfe too blame, becauſe ſhe read no more (as ye heard even now.) She would preſſe nigh, and hearken diligently when any good conference was in hand where ſhe was. She was frequent in prayer, and fervent: and when it was painefull for her to ſpeake, ſhe would aske, <hi>may J not pray in ſpirit?</hi> and anſwer being made that ſhe might, ſhe did accordingly. She would alſo praiſe God for his mercies to her: and in particular for the ſpirituall comforts which he was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14634:12"/> pleaſed to afford unto her. And thus ſhee held on till death deprived her of ability.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt grace wherein ſhe excelled) I had almoſt ſayd all other daughters) was Patience: and whether this grace had not it perfect worke in her, I leave you to judge, when you have heard th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe foure evidences.</p>
            <p n="1">1 She was ſenſible of Gods correcting hand,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh</hi> 1.20. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.3.</note> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the ſmart of his rod, as appeared by this ſpeech, <hi>J am almoſt even tyred with my ſickneſſe, but my hope is J am going to a better place, as for this world, it is full of miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 She was ſilent and free from murmuring and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe. I heard them about her ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.2.40.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the long continuance of her ſickneſſe, and the paine ſhe ſuffered by purging and letting bloud, yet ſhe was never ſeene to open her mouth in diſcontent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be angry or pettiſh with any that were about her.</p>
            <p n="3">3 She did juſtifie God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.75. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12.18. <hi>Eze.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3. <hi>Micha</hi> 7.9.</note> and cleare him in his dealing with her: for being asked, Doe you not thinke God deales very hardly and ſeverely with you in afflicting you ſo ſorely? <hi>No truely doe I not,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>but I thinke he deales with me very well, becauſe I have beene ſo wretched a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 She did ſubmit willingly and obediently to Gods will and pleaſure, as appeared by theſe words of hers:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.41. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>J am very willing, ſaid ſhe, either to live or dye; for if J live, I hope J ſhall live a more godly life, and commit leſſe ſinne of I dye, I ſhall be freed from all ſinne and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſery, whereof this world is very full:</hi> And ſo ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had the better part. And God was pleaſed to give her full
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14634:13"/> aſſurance before her death: for hearing mention of the happineſſe of heaven, ſhe ſpake thus, I know that I ſhall very ſhortly ſee and enjoy it: which ſhe did.</p>
            <q>Sic mihi contingat vivere, ſicque mori.</q>
            <p>I thought it my duty to mention theſe vertues and graces of this ſweet childe of God, my Text calling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>As for her birth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 30.</note> and favour, and beauty, and riches, (the holy Ghoſt telling us they are <hi>deceitfull and vaine</hi>) I thought them not worthy ſo much as of mention.</p>
            <p>Let that which hath beene ſaid in her commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firſt, cauſe us all (eſpecially thoſe who are of more yeares, and farre longer ſtanding in the Schoole of Chriſtianity) to bluſh and be aſhamed and confounded in our ſelves, that we ſhould be thus outſtript in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſelfe-denyall, ſanctification, devotion, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by ſuch a babe in Chriſt, ſuch a childe in yeares.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Let it ſtirre us up and provoke us to imitation: we reade that our Saviour tooke a childe, and ſet him in the midſt of his Diſciples,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18.2.3.</note> and ſaid unto them: <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have after our Saviours example ſet a childe in the midſt of you, and doe aſſure you, that except ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like it in thoſe graces &amp; vertues formerly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, ye ſhall in no wiſe be ſaved: yea, this childe ſhall riſe up in judgement againſt you at the laſt day, and ſo ſhall all her gratious ſpeeches, which I have uttered from her mouth.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14634:13"/>
            <p>I will ſhut up all with a few words of exhortation, unto the worthy Parents of this vertuous childe.</p>
            <p>Foure things I have (right Worſhipfull) to exhort you unto.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 To ſearch and try your wayes. This we are to doe in what affliction ſoever we are.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39.40.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore</hi> (ſaith the Church) <hi>doth the living m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n complaine, a man for the puniſhment of his ſinnes? Let us ſearch and try our wayes, and turne againe to the Lord.</hi> Deſire of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 10.2.</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> did, to ſhew you wherefore he contended with you.</p>
            <p>It may be the ſinne was overloving of your childe; for that is an ordinary fault even in the beſt Parent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we ſee it in <hi>David,</hi> how exceedingly did hee love a naughty ſonne, as appeareth by his exceſſive griefe at his death? <hi>And the king was much moved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33.</note> 
               <hi>and went up to the Chamber over the gate and wept: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he went thus, he ſaid, O my ſonne</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſonne, my ſonne</hi> Abſalom, <hi>would God I had dyed for thee; O</hi> Abſalom, <hi>my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi> It may be you had a male love to your childe, and offered a female to the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 To be thankfull to Almighty God. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us, <hi>in all things to give thankes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Iob</hi> 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>to make our requeſts knowne unto God by prayer and ſupplication with thankeſgiving. Iobs</hi> example is moſt worthy of your imitation, who at the loſſe of his Cattell, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Children, ſaid, <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More eſpecially let me exhort you to thankeſgiving to God for theſe three b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ries.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14634:14"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4.</note>1 For making you inſtruments of bringing forth ſuch a childe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath beene deſcribed. I may ſay to you, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in another caſe did to the Romans, <hi>Yee have brought forth fruit unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 For arming you with ſuch courage and patience, in bearing ſo great a loſſe ſo quietly and obediently, and that you are come to ſee her committed to the ground, with as much cheerefulneſſe, as the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſees his pretious ſeed caſt into the earth, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with cloddes: which he values at as high a rate, as that which he reſerves at home: as knowing that though her body lye a while in the grave, yet it ſhall ſhortly riſe a glorious body, as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like his glorious body:</hi> and <hi>ſhall ſhine forth as the Sunne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 13.43.</note> 
               <hi>in the kingdome of her Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 For giving you ſuch cauſe of patience, and ground of comfort.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In that he hath removed that thing from you, which might have ſtollen your hearts from him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In that he gave <hi>you</hi> ſuch aſſured evidences of grace in her, before her death; and <hi>her</hi> aſſurance of ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 In taking her away ſo ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, without the leaſt paine or ſtrugling.</p>
            <p n="4">4 In infuſing ſuch comforts into your ſoules, even in the time of her diſſolution, that you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> rejoyced for her gaine, then ſorrowed for your owne loſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3 To draw nearer unto God, and to have more fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him in his ordinances: and you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:14634:14"/> finde the comfort of your childe in God, who will be better to you then ten daugthers: y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, he will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence your loſſes to you, if not in the ſame,<note place="margin">1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet in ſome other kinde, as he ſhall ſee it beſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his owne glory, and your comfort.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4 To bury all your ſorrow for her, in the grave with her, and let it riſe no more: Put on <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution. <hi>While the childe was yet alive, I faſted and wept,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>for I ſaid, who can tell whether God will be gratious unto me, that the childe may live? But now he is dead, wherefore ſhould I faſt? can I bring him backe againe?</hi> Goe hence with as much comfort, as if you had matched her to the greateſt prince on earth. Doe as the wiſe man coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth, <hi>Goe thy way, eate thy bread with joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>and drinke thy wine with a merry heart, for God accepteth thy works. Let thy garments alwaies be white, and let thy head lacke no oyle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You rejoyced on the day of her birth: why then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce now; for the day of death is the ſoules birth-day. And the Preacher telleth us (ſpeaking onely of ſuch as ſhe was) <hi>That the day of their death is better then the day of their birth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude all with that adviſe of <hi>Nehemiah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Goe your way, mourne not, neither be ſorry: for the joy of the Lord is your ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14634:15"/>
            <head>Her Epitaph by the Author.</head>
            <l>BIrth, breeding, beauty, grace, &amp; carriage ſweet</l>
            <l>In thee deare Saint, did all together meet:</l>
            <l>The Sunne ne're ſaw a lovelier face than thine,</l>
            <l>Nor heaven receiv'd a ſpirit more divine.</l>
            <l>Thrice happy Parents ſuch a childe to breed,</l>
            <l>Begot againe of Gods immortall ſeed.</l>
            <l>Ceaſe ſorrowing then, ſith Saints &amp; Angels ſing</l>
            <l>To ſee her match'd with an eternall King.</l>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
